<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This is built from a template for a generic Internet Draft. Suggestions for
     improvement welcome - write to Brian Carpenter, brian.e.carpenter @ gmail.com 
     This can be converted using the Web service at http://xml.resource.org/ -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- You want a table of contents -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- Use symbolic labels for references -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<!-- This sorts the references -->
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<!-- Change to "yes" if someone has disclosed IPR for the draft -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!-- This defines the specific filename and version number of your draft (and inserts the appropriate IETF boilerplate -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-carpenter-anima-ani-objectives-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ANI GRASP Objectives">Technical Objectives for the Autonomic Network Infrastructure</title>

    <author fullname="Brian Carpenter" initials="B. E." surname="Carpenter">
      <organization abbrev="Univ. of Auckland"/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>
          <street>University of Auckland</street>
          <street>PB 92019</street>
          <city>Auckland</city>
          <region/>
          <code>1142</code>
          <country>New Zealand</country>
        </postal>
        <email>brian.e.carpenter@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Bing Liu" initials="B." surname="Liu">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus</street>
          <street>No.156 Beiqing Road</street>
          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing</city>
          <code>100095</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>leo.liubing@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

 

    <date day="18" month="November" year="2016"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines several technical objectives for the
      Generic Autonomic Signaling Protocol (GRASP) for use by components
      of the Autonomic Networking Infrastructure outlined in the ANIMA reference model.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
      This document defines several technical objectives for use with for the
      Generic Autonomic Signaling Protocol (GRASP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>.
      They are intended for use by corresponding Autonomic Service Agents
     (ASAs) that realise infrastructure components of the Autonomic Network
     Infrastructure (ANI) outlined in the ANIMA reference model <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-reference-model"/>.
     Also other early use cases are in scope.
     </t>
     
    <t>Note: This draft is posted to allow systematic discussion of the various objectives in a
     consistent way. It is quite probable that rather
     than this being published as an RFC, the various objective definitions will be incorporated directly in the
     relevant specifications. </t> 
            
    <t>The reference model identifies several infrastructure components that will fit together
    to form the ANI, and early use cases for ANIMA are also considered:</t>
    <t><list>
    <t>Secure Bootstrap.</t>
    <t>Autonomic Control Plane (ACP).</t>
    <t>Stable Connectivity of Network OAM.</t>
    <t>Intent Distribution.</t>
    <t>Prefix Management</t>
    </list></t>
    
    <t>The following sections define GRASP objectives for each of these cases. They are
    described an informal object notation and formally using CBOR data definition language (CDDL)
    <xref target="I-D.greevenbosch-appsawg-cbor-cddl"/>.
    Undefined CDDL terms are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>.</t>
     


    </section>

    <section title="Objectives for Secure Bootstrap">
    <t>Three components are involved in the Bootstrapping Remote Secure Key Infrastructures (BRSKI) process
    described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"/>: the Registrar, the Join Assistant (or Proxy),
    and the Joining Node (or Pledge). The proxy and the pledge are attached to the same link-layer and use
    link-local communications only, to minimize exposure to eavesdroppers and malicious nodes. There may be
    multiple hops between the proxy and the registrar. Therefore, two different GRASP objectives are
    required: one that is used over an existing secure network between the registrar and the proxy,
    and another that is used over an insecure link-local hop between the proxy and the pledge.
    The security aspects and the corresponding limited instances of GRASP
    are discussed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"/>
    and <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>.</t>
    
    <t>Note that since secure bootstrap takes place, by definition, on an incompletely secure
    network, the use of any protocol needs to be kept as simple and limited as possible.
    Therefore, only one GRASP message type is used - flooding - to avoid giving away any
    unnecessary information by any node involved.</t>
    
    <t>A registrar announces itself to potential proxies by use of the "AN_registrar" objective.
    This is a synchronization objective primarily intended to be flooded throughout the network using the
    GRASP Flood Synchronization (M_FLOOD) message. In accordance with the design of the Flood message,
    a locator consisting of a specific IP address, IP protocol number and port number will be distributed
    with the flooded objective. An example of the objective is informally:</t>
    <t>
    ["AN_registrar", F_SYNCH, loop_count, [7, "BRSKI-TLS"]]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is
    </t><t>
    registrar-objective = ["AN_registrar", F_SYNCH, loop-count, [radius, method]]
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    radius = uint ; loop-count at the source node
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    method = text ; name of the BRSKI method supported
    </t>
    <t>
    The 'radius' parameter allows a proxy that receives this message to determine its distance in hops
    from the registrar, by subtracting the received 'loop-count' from 'radius'.
    </t>
    <t>The 'method' parameter indicates the specific BRSKI method available at the given locator. The initial possible values
    are "BRSKI-TLS" and "BRSKI-COAP". A registrar that supports more than one method will flood multiple versions
    of the "AN_registrar" objective.</t>
    
    <section title="Flooding Alternative for Proxy">
    
    <t>A proxy announces itself to potential pledges by use of the "AN_proxy" objective.
    This is a synchronization objective primarily intended to be flooded on a single link using the
    GRASP Flood Synchronization (M_FLOOD) message. In accordance with the design of the Flood message,
    a locator consisting of a specific link-local IP address, IP protocol number and port number will be distributed
    with the flooded objective. An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_proxy", F_SYNCH, 1, "BRSKI-TLS"]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is
    </t><t>
    proxy-objective = ["AN_proxy", F_SYNCH, 1, method]
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    method = text ; name of the BRSKI method supported
    </t>
    
    <t>
    The loop-count is fixed at 1 since this is a link-local operation.
    </t>
    <t>The 'method' parameter indicates the specific BRSKI method available at the given locator. The initial possible values
    are "BRSKI-TLS" and "BRSKI-COAP". A proxy that supports more than one method will flood multiple versions
    of the "AN_proxy" objective.</t>
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="Negotiation Alternative for Proxy">
    <t>This alternative to "AN_proxy" uses additional features of GRASP.
    It requires additional complexity in the pledge, and requires the pledge to announce its existence
    to any on-link eavesdroppers via a Discovery message. It is therefore not recommended on security
    grounds, but is defined here for completeness.</t>
    <t>A pledge discovers a local proxy and negotiates a BRSKI method with it by use of the "AN_join" objective.
    First, the pledge performs GRASP discovery, with the loop-count set to 1 and limited to
    link-local addresses. If multiple responses occur, it chooses one by an 
    implementation-defined method. Then the pledge initiates GRASP negotiation to choose a mutually
    acceptable BRSKI method.</t><t>
    An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_join", F_NEG, 6, ["BRSKI-COAP","BRSKI-TLS"]]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is
    </t><t>
    join-objective = ["AN_join", F_NEG, loop-count, [*method]]
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    method = text ; name of the BRSKI method supported
    </t>
    <t>The parties will negotiate until one side proposes a single BRSKI method and the other side accepts. In the simplest
    case of immediate acceptance, there will only be two messages (Request Negotiate and End Negotiate).    
    The locator (IP address, IP protocol number, port number) used for the negotiation
    will be available for the subsequent BRSKI operations, if required.</t>
    <t>Note that in the Discovery message, the loop count will be set to 1 to limit discovery
    to the local link. In the negotiation stage, the loop count will serve its normal
    purpose (limiting the negotiation to 6 steps in the above example).</t>
    </section>
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="Objective for Autonomic Control Plane">
    <t>The Autonomic Control Plane (ACP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-autonomic-control-plane"/>
    constructs itself without outside intervention. To achieve this, each node needs to identify its
    link-local neighbors on all interfaces, and agree on a secure connection method with each of them.
    There are at least two possible approaches for this: a flooding mechanism, in which each node
    announces itself and it security methods to its neighbors, or a discovery and negotiation mechanism,
    in which each node actively discovers its neighbors. For the moment this draft describes both methods. </t>
    
    <t>For either method, each node runs an ASA that supports the corresponding objective. This ASA runs
    permanently, in order to discover or detect new ACP neighbors or to remove failed neighbors.</t>
    
    <section title="Flooding Alternative">
    
     <t>A node announces itself to potential ACP peers by use of the "AN_ACP" objective.
    This is a synchronization objective primarily intended to be flooded on a single link using the
    GRASP Flood Synchronization (M_FLOOD) message. In accordance with the design of the Flood message,
    a locator consisting of a specific link-local IP address, IP protocol number and port number will be distributed
    with the flooded objective. An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_ACP", F_SYNCH, 1, "IKEv2"]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is
    </t><t>
    acp-objective = ["AN_ACP", F_SYNCH, 1, method]
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    method = text ; name of the connection method supported
    </t>
    
    <t>
    The loop-count is fixed at 1 since this is a link-local operation.
    </t>
    <t>The 'method' parameter indicates the specific connection method available at the given locator. The initial possible values
    are "IKEv2" and "TLS". A node that supports more than one method will flood multiple versions
    of the "AN_ACP" objective.</t>
    
    <t>Note that a node serving both as an ACP node and BRSKI proxy may choose to distribute the "AN_ACP" objectives
    and "AN_proxy" objectives in the same message, since GRASP allows multiple objectives in one Flood message.</t>
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="Negotiation Alternative">
    
    <t>Each node discovers its neighbours and negotiates a connection method with each one by use of the "AN_ACP" objective.
    First, the node performs GRASP discovery, with the loop-count set to 1 and limited to
    link-local addresses. It records each response that it receives within the chosen discovery timeout.
    Then the pledge initiates GRASP negotiation with each newly discovered peer in turn to choose a mutually
    acceptable connection method.</t><t>
    An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_ACP", F_NEG, 6, ["IKEv2","TLS"]]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is
    </t><t>
    acp-objective = ["AN_ACP", F_NEG, loop-count, [*method]]
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    method = text ; name of the connection method supported
    </t>
    <t>The parties will negotiate until one side proposes a single connection method and the other side accepts. In the simplest
    case of immediate acceptance, there will only be two messages (Request Negotiate and End Negotiate).    
    The locator (IP address, IP protocol number, port number) used for the negotiation
    will be available for the subsequent operations, if required.</t>
    <t>Note that in the Discovery message, the loop count will be set to 1 to limit discovery
    to the local link. In the negotiation stage, the loop count will serve its normal
    purpose (limiting the negotiation to 6 steps in the above example).</t>
    </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Objective for Stable Connectivity of Network OAM">
    <t>For OAM purposes <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-stable-connectivity"/>,
    a special-purpose ASA, which we will call the NOC ASA, mediates connectivity
    between NOC systems performing OAM operations and autonomic nodes that can be
    reached securely via the ACP. This is requires s discovery operation, which could
    be handled in two ways: the NOC ASA discovers all nodes, or each node discovers the NOC ASA.
    The latter seems much more practical. However, the NOC will need to know something
    about each target node, so the corresponding objective is defined as a negotiation
    objective to allow for this.</t>
    <t>
    An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_NOC", F_NEG, 6, [TBD]]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is
    </t><t>
    noc-objective = ["AN_NOC", F_NEG, loop-count, [TBD]]
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    TBD = any ; node information to be defined
    </t>
    <t>When a node joins the ACP, one of its initial actions must be to perform GRASP discovery for "AN_NOC"
    and then to send a Request Negotiate message to the NOC ASA supplying TBD. If successfully received,
    the NOC ASA must rely with an End Negotiate message. From then on, any OAM communication between the
    NOC and the node in question will proceed over the ACP using the information TBD.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Objectives for Intent Distribution">
    <t>The format and semantics of Intent are not yet defined, although some
    aspects are discussed in <xref target="I-D.du-anima-an-intent"/>.
    Here we assume that Intent is supplied to the whole network as a single
    file and that the file is obtained by each node that needs it via a
    specific Uniform Resource Identifier, typically a URL. We also assume that
    Intent, within a given autonomic domain, is qualified by a monotonically
    increasing version number, so that nodes can determine if their current
    copy of Intent is out of date. (A timestamp is not used for this purpose,
    since it would depend on all nodes having consistent clocks.)</t>
    
    <t>Thus, a source of Intent announces itself to all nodes by use of the "AN_intent" objective.
    This is a synchronization objective primarily intended to be flooded using the
    GRASP Flood Synchronization (M_FLOOD) message. An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_intent", F_SYNCH, loop_count, [12345, "https://noc.example.com/Intent/"]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is
    </t><t>
    intent-objective = ["AN_Intent", F_SYNCH, loop-count, [version-number,uri]]
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    version-number = uint
    <vspace blankLines="0"/>
    uri = text             ; URI conforming to RFC 3986
    </t>
    <t>A node that needs to obtain or update Intent will use the latest received
    version of this objective to check if the version number has increased, and will
    use the given URI to obtain the current Intent if necessary.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Objective for Prefix Management">
    <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Flood Frequency">
    <t>Any ASA that floods one of the above objectives should do so at a carefully
    chosen frequency. Recipient nodes may be starting up, reconnecting, or waking up from sleep,
    so floods need to be refreshed periodically. On the other hand, excessive flooding will
    consume bandwidth, CPU and battery capacity throughout the network, and might even
    resemble a DoS attack. A general guideline is to flood an objective once immediately
    after its value is initialised or changed, and then repeat the flood at intervals
    of at least 30 seconds. Additionally, the flooding interval should be slightly
    jittered to avoid synchronicity with other floods. Finally, the value of a flooded objective
    should change as rarely as possible (on a timescale of at least minutes, not seconds).</t>
    </section>
    

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>General security issues for GRASP are covered in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>. Specific
      issues that are not mentioned above are discussed in the referenced drafts for BRSKI, ACP,
      stable connectivity and Intent.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to add the following entries to the GRASP Objective Names Table
      registry created by <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>:
      <vspace blankLines="0"/>
      AN_registrar
      <vspace blankLines="0"/>
      AN_proxy
      <vspace blankLines="0"/>
      AN_ACP
      <vspace blankLines="0"/>
      AN_NOC
      <vspace blankLines="0"/>
      AN_intent
       </t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
     
  
    
    <references title="Normative References">
      
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-grasp'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.greevenbosch-appsawg-cbor-cddl'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
    
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-autonomic-control-plane'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-reference-model'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-stable-connectivity'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.du-anima-an-intent'?> 
      
    </references>
    
  <section anchor="changes" title="Change log [RFC Editor: Please remove]">
      
    <t>draft-carpenter-anima-ani-objectives-00, 2018-11-15:
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
       Initial version</t>  
    </section>   
  </back>
</rfc>
