<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This is built from a template for a generic Internet Draft. Suggestions for
     improvement welcome - write to Brian Carpenter, brian.e.carpenter @ gmail.com 
     This can be converted using the Web service at https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/ -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- You want a table of contents -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- Use symbolic labels for references -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<!-- This sorts the references -->
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<!-- Change to "yes" if someone has disclosed IPR for the draft -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!-- This defines the specific filename and version number of your draft (and inserts the appropriate IETF boilerplate -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-carpenter-anima-ani-objectives-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ANI GRASP Objectives">Technical Objective Formats for the Autonomic Network Infrastructure</title>

    <author fullname="Brian Carpenter" initials="B. E." surname="Carpenter">
      <organization abbrev="Univ. of Auckland"/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>
          <street>University of Auckland</street>
          <street>PB 92019</street>
          <city>Auckland</city>
          <region/>
          <code>1142</code>
          <country>New Zealand</country>
        </postal>
        <email>brian.e.carpenter@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Bing Liu" initials="B." surname="Liu">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q22, Huawei Campus</street>
          <street>No.156 Beiqing Road</street>
          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing</city>
          <code>100095</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>leo.liubing@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

 

    <date day="30" month="June" year="2017"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines the formats of several technical objectives for the
      Generic Autonomic Signaling Protocol (GRASP) used by components
      of the Autonomic Networking Infrastructure outlined in the ANIMA reference model.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
      This document defines several technical objectives for use with for the
      Generic Autonomic Signaling Protocol (GRASP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>.
      They are intended for use by corresponding Autonomic Service Agents
     (ASAs) that support infrastructure components of the Autonomic Network
     Infrastructure (ANI) outlined in the ANIMA reference model <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-reference-model"/>.
     </t>
     
    <t>Note: This draft is posted to allow systematic discussion of the various objectives in a
     consistent way. It is possible that rather
     than this being published as an RFC, the various objective definitions will be incorporated directly in the
     relevant specifications. </t> 
            
    <t>The reference model identifies several infrastructure components that will fit together
    with GRASP to form the ANI:</t>
    <t><list>
    <t>Secure Bootstrap.</t>
    <t>Autonomic Control Plane (ACP).</t>
    <t>Stable Connectivity of Network OAM.</t>
    </list></t>
    
    <t>The following sections define GRASP objectives for each of these cases. They are
    described in an informal object notation and formally using CBOR data definition language (CDDL)
    <xref target="I-D.greevenbosch-appsawg-cbor-cddl"/>.
    Undefined CDDL terms are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>.</t>
     


  </section>

  <section title="Objectives for Secure Bootstrap">
    <t>Three ANI components are involved in the Bootstrapping Remote Secure Key Infrastructures (BRSKI) process
    described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"/>: the Join Registrar, the Join Proxy,
    and the Pledge (a node joining the domain). In the present document we only consider interactions between autonomic
    nodes involved in BRSKI; non-autonomic nodes are expected to use different methods not involving GRASP.</t>
    
    <t>Note that since secure bootstrap takes place, by definition, on an incompletely secure
    network, the use of any protocol needs to be kept as simple and limited as possible.
    Between the proxy and the pledge, therefore, only one GRASP message type is
    used - flooding - to avoid giving away any unnecessary information.    
    The  proxy and pledge have a link-local connection between them. Mutual discovery and
    bootstrap can happen without any prior provisioning of helper information
    by an external mechanism. Instead, link-local multicast with GRASP is used. 
    This will minimize exposure to eavesdroppers and malicious nodes. 
    On the other hand, there may be multiple physical hops between the proxy and the
    registrar. Therefore, two different GRASP objectives are
    required: one that is used over an existing secure network (typically the ACP)
    between the registrar and the proxy, and another that is used over an insecure
    link-local hop between the proxy and the pledge. Furher security aspects
    are discussed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra"/>
    and <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>.</t>
    
    <section title="Additional value for GRASP message syntax">
    <t>This document extends the syntax of the GRASP protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>
    by adding an additional value for the "transport-proto" element:</t>
    <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
  transport-proto /= IPPROTO_IP
  IPPROTO_IP = 41
]]></artwork>  
    </figure>
    <t>This value indicates IP-in-IP encapsulation.</t>
    </section>
      
    <section title="Discovered Sychronization Objective for the Join Registrar">
    <t>The Join Proxy discovers a Join Registrar by using the "AN_join_registrar" GRASP objective.
    It must only be used when GRASP is running securely, typically because the
    Join Proxy is in a node that has already joined the ACP.
    The value of the objective will indicate the BRSKI methods supported
    by the registrar and the corresponding locators for BRSKI traffic.</t>
    <t>
    First, the pledge performs GRASP discovery. If multiple responses occur, it chooses one by an 
    implementation-defined method. Then the pledge initiates GRASP synchronization to obtain the
    BRSKI methods supported by the discovered registrar. Alternatively, if implemented, GRASP
    rapid mode could be used to combine the two operations.</t><t>
    An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_join_registrar", SYNCH-FLAG, 6, [["BRSKI-TCP", [O_IPv6_LOCATOR, fd45:1345::6789, 6, 443]]]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is:
    </t><figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
  registrar-objective = ["AN_join_registrar", objective-flags,
                         loop-count, [*[method, locator-option]]]
  
  objective-flags = ; as in the GRASP specification
  loop-count =      ; as in the GRASP specification
  locator-option =  ; as in the GRASP specification
  method = "BRSKI-TCP" / "BRSKI-UDP" / "BRSKI-IPIP"
                    ; name of the BRSKI method supported
 
]]></artwork>  
    </figure>
    
    <t>The objective-flags field is set to indicate synchronization.</t>
    <t>The loop-count is set to a suitable value to limit the scope of discovery. A suggested default value is 6.</t>
    <t>The Join Proxy, upon receiving this objective, will select one or more
    of the methods for announcement to Pledges. It will store the provided
    locator for each method for subsequent BRSKI operations.
    Note that this locator is distinct from the locator for the Join Registrar's
    ASA, which is used only for GRASP operations.</t>
    </section>
    

    
    <section title="Flooded Objective for Join Proxy">
    
    <t>A Join Proxy announces itself to potential pledges by use of the "AN_join_proxy" objective.
    This is a synchronization objective intended only to be flooded on a single link using the
    GRASP Flood Synchronization (M_FLOOD) message. In accordance with the design of the Flood message,
    a locator consisting of a specific link-local IP address, IP protocol number and port number will be distributed
    with the flooded objective. An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_join_proxy", SYNCH-FLAG, 1, "BRSKI-TCP"]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is:
    </t><figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
  proxy-objective = ["AN_join_proxy", objective-flags, loop-count,
                     method]
  
  objective-flags = ; as in the GRASP specification
  loop-count = 1    ; limit to link-local operation
  method = "BRSKI-TCP" / "BRSKI-UDP" / "BRSKI-IPIP"
]]></artwork>  
    </figure>
    
    <t>The objective-flags field is set to indicate synchronization.</t>
    <t>The loop-count is fixed at 1 since this is a link-local operation.</t>
    <t>The 'method' parameter indicates the specific BRSKI method available at the given locator. 
       A Join Proxy that supports more than one method will flood multiple versions
       of the "AN_join_proxy" objective.</t>
    <t>Thus, a proxy that floods this objective with the value "BRSKI-IPIP" will attach a locator
    option such as the following to it:</t>
    <t>[O_IPv6_LOCATOR, ipv6-address, IPPROTO_IP, nil]</t>
    <t>where 'ipv6-address' is the link-local address of the proxy. Similarly, locators for "BRSKI-TCP"
    and "BRSKI-UDP" would be:</t>
    <t>[O_IPv6_LOCATOR, ipv6-address, IPPROTO_TCP, port]</t>
    <t>[O_IPv6_LOCATOR, ipv6-address, IPPROTO_UDP, port]</t>
    <t>By this mechanism, a proxy may announce one or more connection methods to all pledges,
    each with an associated link-local address, protocol number and port number.</t>
    </section>
    
    
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="Objective for Autonomic Control Plane">
    <t>The Autonomic Control Plane (ACP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-autonomic-control-plane"/>
    constructs itself without outside intervention. To achieve this, each node needs to identify its
    link-local neighbors on all interfaces, and agree on a secure connection method with each of them.
    As for the Join Proxy, a flooding mechanism, in which each node
    announces itself and it security methods to its neighbors, is used. </t>
    
    <t>Thus each autonomic node runs an ASA that supports the corresponding objective.
    This ASA runs permanently, as long as the node is capable of being part of the ACP,
    in order to discover or detect new ACP neighbors or to remove failed neighbors.</t>
    
     <t>A node announces itself to potential ACP peers by use of the "AN_ACP" objective.
    This is a synchronization objective intended to be flooded on a single link using the
    GRASP Flood Synchronization (M_FLOOD) message. In accordance with the design of the Flood message,
    a locator consisting of a specific link-local IP address, IP protocol number and port number
    will be distributed with the flooded objective. An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_ACP", SYNCH-FLAG, 1, ["IKEv2","TLS"]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is:
    </t><figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
  acp-objective = ["AN_ACP", objective-flags, loop-count, method]
  
  objective-flags = ; as in the GRASP specification
  loop-count = 1    ; limit to link-local operation
  method = text     ; name of the connection method supported
 ]]></artwork>  
    </figure>
    
    <t>The objective-flags field is set to indicate synchronization.</t>
    <t>The loop-count is fixed at 1 since this is a link-local operation.</t>
    <t>The 'method' parameter indicates the specific connection method available at the given locator. The initial possible values
    are "IKEv2", "GRE-IKEv2", "TLS" and "dTLS". A node that supports more than one method may flood multiple versions
    of the "AN_ACP" objective, each accompanied by its own locator.</t>
    
    <t>Note that a node serving both as an ACP node and BRSKI Join Proxy may choose to distribute the "AN_ACP" objective
    and "AN_join_proxy" objective in the same flood message, since GRASP allows multiple objectives in one Flood message.</t>
    
    
    </section>
    
    <section title="Objective for Stable Connectivity of Network OAM">
    <t>For OAM purposes <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-stable-connectivity"/>,
    a special-purpose ASA, which we will call the NOC ASA, mediates connectivity
    between NOC systems performing OAM operations and autonomic nodes that can be
    reached securely via the ACP. This requires a discovery operation, which could
    be handled in two ways: the NOC ASA discovers all nodes, or each node discovers the NOC ASA.
    The latter seems much more practical. However, the NOC will need to know something
    about each target node, so the corresponding objective is defined as a negotiation
    objective to allow for this.</t>
    <t>
    An example of the objective is informally:
    </t><t>
    ["AN_NOC", NEG-FLAG, 6, [TBD]]
    </t><t>
    The formal CDDL definition is:
    </t>
    <figure>
    <artwork><![CDATA[
  noc-objective = ["AN_NOC", objective-flags, loop-count, [TBD]]
  
  objective-flags = ; as in the GRASP specification
  TBD = any ; node information to be defined
]]></artwork>  
    </figure>    
    <t>The objective-flags field is set to indicate negotiation.</t>
    <t>Dry run mode must not be used.</t>
    <t>The loop-count is set to a suitable value to limit the scope of discovery. A suggested default value is 6.</t>
    <t>When a node joins the ACP, one of its initial actions must be to perform GRASP discovery for "AN_NOC"
    and then to send a Request Negotiate message to the NOC ASA supplying the value TBD. If successfully received,
    the NOC ASA must reply with an End Negotiate message. From then on, any OAM communication between the
    NOC and the node in question will proceed over the ACP using the information TBD.</t>
    </section>
    
  
    <section title="Flood Frequency">
    <t>Any ASA that floods one of the above objectives should do so at a carefully
    chosen frequency. Recipient nodes may be starting up, reconnecting, or waking up from sleep,
    so floods need to be refreshed periodically. On the other hand, excessive flooding will
    consume bandwidth, CPU and battery capacity throughout the network, and might even
    resemble a DoS attack. A general guideline is to flood an objective once immediately
    after its value is initialised or changed, and then repeat the flood at intervals
    of at least 30 seconds. Additionally, the flooding interval should be slightly
    jittered to avoid synchronicity with other floods. Finally, the value of a flooded objective
    should change as rarely as possible (on a timescale of at least minutes, not seconds).</t>
    </section>
    

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>General security issues for GRASP are covered in <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>.
      The objectives "AN_join_proxy" and "AN_ACP" must be implemented using a DULL instance of
      GRASP. Specific issues not mentioned above are discussed in the referenced drafts for each use case.
      </t>
      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to add the following entries to the GRASP Objective Names Table
      registry created by <xref target="I-D.ietf-anima-grasp"/>:
      <figure>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
      AN_join_registrar
      AN_join_proxy
      AN_ACP
      AN_NOC
]]></artwork>
    </figure>
       </t>

 
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Valuable comments were made by
      Toerless Eckert,
      Max Pritikin,
      and Michael Richardson.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
     
  
    
    <references title="Normative References">
      
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-grasp'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.greevenbosch-appsawg-cbor-cddl'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
    
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-autonomic-control-plane'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-reference-model'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-bootstrapping-keyinfra'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-anima-stable-connectivity'?>
      
    </references>
    
  <section anchor="changes" title="Change log [RFC Editor: Please remove]">
      <t>draft-carpenter-anima-ani-objectives-02, 2017-06-30:
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
       Limited scope to initial ANI components
       <vspace blankLines="1"/>
       Updated details and removed alternatives
      </t>
  
    <t>draft-carpenter-anima-ani-objectives-01, 2017-02-13:
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
       Added prefix management case
       <vspace blankLines="1"/>
       Updated objectives for BRSKI
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
       Editorial corrections</t>  
       
    <t>draft-carpenter-anima-ani-objectives-00, 2016-11-15:
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
       Initial version</t>  
    </section>   
  </back>
</rfc>
